The humanitarian model has barely changed
نموذج العمل الإنساني بالكاد تغير
since the early 20th century.
منذ بداية القرن العشرين.
Its origins are firmly rooted
أصوله متجذرة راسخة
in the analog age.
في العصر التناظري.
And there is a major shift coming on the horizon.
وهناك تغير كبير يلوح في الأفق.
The catalyst for this change
حفاز هذا التغير
was the major earthquake that struck Haiti
كان الزلزال الهائل الذي ضرب هاييتي
on the 12th of January in 2010.
في ال12 من يناير 2010.
Haiti was a game changer.
هاييتي غيرت قواعد اللعبة.
The earthquake destroyed the capital of Port-au-Prince,
دمر الزلزال العاصمة بورت أو برنس،
claiming the lives of some 320,000 people,
موديا بحياة حوالي 320,000 شخص،
rendering homeless
وقام بتشريد
about 1.2 million people.
حوالي 1.2 مليون شخص.
Government institutions were completely decapitated,
المؤسسات الحكومية قطع رأسها،
including the presidential palace.
بما في ذلك القصر الرئاسي.
I remember standing
أتذكر الوقوف
on the roof of the Ministry of Justice
على سطح وزارة العدل
in downtown Port-au-Prince.
في وسط مدينة بورت أو برنس.
It was about two meters high,
كان مرتفعا بحوالي المترين،
completely squashed
تم سحقه بالكامل
by the violence of the earthquake.
بقوة الزلزال.
For those of us on the ground in those early days,
لمن كان منا على الأرض في تلك الأيام الأولى،
it was clear for even the most disaster-hardened veterans
كان من الواضح حتى بالنسبة للقدماء ممن قوتهم الكوارث
that Haiti was something different.
أن هاييتي كانت شيئا مختلفا.
Haiti was something we hadn't seen before.
هاييتي كانت شيئا لم نره من قبل.
But Haiti provided us with something else unprecedented.
لكن هاييتي زودتنا بأمر آخر غير مسبوق.
Haiti allowed us to glimpse into a future
هاييتي أعطتنا نبذة عن مستقبل
of what disaster response might look like
ما ستبدو عليه الاستجابة للكوارث
in a hyper-connected world
في عالم شديد الاتصال
where people have access
حيث يستطيع الناس الحصول على
to mobile smart devices.
أجهزة محمولة ذكية.
Because out of the urban devastation
لأنه من الدمار الحضاري
in Port-au-Prince
في بورت أو برنس
came a torrent of SMS texts --
جاء سيل من الرسائل القصيرة --
people crying for help,
أشخاص يصرخون طلبا للمساعدة،
beseeching us for assistance,
يتضرعون لنا للمساعدة،
sharing data, offering support,
يتشاركون البيانات، يعرضون الدعم
looking for their loved ones.
يبحثون عن أحبائهم.
This was a situation
كانت هذه وضعية
that traditional aid agencies had never before encountered.
لم تصادفها قط وكالات المساعدة التقليدية من قبل.
We were in one of the poorest countries on the planet,
كنا في واحدة من أفقر الدول على الكوكب،
but 80 percent of the people
لكن 80 في المئة من الناس
had mobile devices in their hands.
يمتلكون جهازا محمولا في أيديهم.
And we were unprepared for this,
ولم نكن مستعدين لهذا،
and they were shaping the aid effort.
كانوا يشكلون جهود المساعدة.
Outside Haiti also, things were looking different.
كانت الأمور تبدو مختلفة خارج هاييتي كذلك،
Tens of thousands of so-called digital volunteers
عشرات الألوف مما يسمى المتطوعون الرقميون
were scouring the Internet,
كانوا يجوبون الانترنت،
converting tweets
محولين تغريدات تويتر
that had already been converted from texts
التي تم تحويلها من الرسائل النصية
and putting these into open-source maps,
ويضعونها في خرائط مفتوحة المصدر،
layering them with all sorts of important information --
مصففين إياها بكل أنواع المعلومات المهمة --
people like Crisis Mappers and Open Street Map --
أشخاص مثل راسم خرائط الكوارث و خارطة الشارع المفتوحة --
and putting these on the Web for everybody --
ويضعون هذا في الانترنت للجميع --
the media, the aid organizations and the communities themselves --
وسائل الإعلام، هيئات المساعدة والمجتمعات نفسها --
to participate in and to use.
للمساهمة والاستفادة.
Back in Haiti,
في هاييتي،
people were increasingly turning
كان الناس يتجهون بتزايد
to the medium of SMS.
نحو الرسائل النصية كوسيلة.
People that were hungry and hurting
الناس الذين كانوا جوعانين ومصابين
were signaling their distress,
كانوا يبثون محنتهم،
were signaling their need for help.
كانوا يبثون حاجتهم للمساعدة.
On street sides all over Port-au-Prince,
على جانبي الشارع على طول بورت او برنس،
entrepreneurs sprung up
ظهر صغار اصحاب الاعمال
offering mobile phone charging stations.
يعرضون محطات شحن الهاتف النقال.
They understood more than we did
فهموا أكثر منا
people's innate need
حاجة الناس الفطرية
to be connected.
للاتصال.
Never having been confronted
لم نواجه قط
with this type of situation before,
هذا النوع من المواقف من قبل،
we wanted to try and understand
أردنا أن نحاول فهم
how we could tap into this incredible resource,
كيف يمكننا الاستفادة من هذا المصدر المذهل،
how we could really leverage
كيف يمكننا بالفعل استغلال
this incredible use of mobile technology
هذا الاستعمال المذهل للتكنولوجيا المحمولة
and SMS technology.
وتكنولوجيا الرسائل النصية.
We started talking with a local telecom provider called Voilà,
بدأنا نتحدث مع شركة اتصالات محلية تدعى فويلا Voilà،
which is a subsidiary of Trilogy International.
والتي هي فرع لشركة تريولوجي العالمية Trilogy .
We had basically three requirements.
كان لدينا ثلاث متطلبات أساسية.
We wanted to communicate
أردنا التواصل
in a two-way form of communication.
بطريقة تواصل ثنائية.
We didn't want to shout; we needed to listen as well.
لم نرد الصراخ؛ نحتاج إلى الاستماع كذلك.
We wanted to be able to target
أردنا أن نكون قادرين على التصويب
specific geographic communities.
نحو تجمعات جغرافية معينة.
We didn't need to talk to the whole country at the same time.
لم نحتج إلى الحديث مع كامل الدولة في نفس الوقت.
And we wanted it to be easy to use.
وأردناه أن يكون سهل الاستعمال.
Out of this rubble of Haiti and from this devastation
من أنقاض هاييتي ومن هذا الدمار
came something that we call TERA --
خرج للوجود شيء سميناه تيرا TERA --
the Trilogy Emergency Response Application --
تطبيق تريلوجي للاستجابة الطارئة --
which has been used to support the aid effort
والذي تم استعماله لدعم جهود المساعدة
ever since.
منذ ذلك الحين.
It has been used to help communities prepare for disasters.
تم استخدامه لمساعدة المجتمعات على الاستعداد للكوارث.
It has been used to signal early warning
تم استخدامه لإرسال إشارة تحذير مبكرة
in advance of weather-related disasters.
قبل الكوارث المرتبطة بالأحوال الجوية.
It's used for public health awareness campaigns
يتم استخدامه في حملات التوعية الصحية العامة
such as the prevention of cholera.
مثل الوقاية من الكوليرا.
And it is even used for sensitive issues
وقد تم استخدامه في مواضيع حساسة
such as building awareness
مثل بناء الوعي
around gender-based violence.
بخصوص العنف القائم على الجنس.
But does it work?
لكن هل يشتغل؟
We have just published
قمنا للتو بنشر
an evaluation of this program,
تقييم لهذا البرنامج،
and the evidence that is there for all to see
والدليل المتوفر للجميع ليروه
is quite remarkable.
لافت للغاية.
Some 74 percent of people
حوالي 74 في المئة من الناس
received the data.
استقبلوا البيانات.
Those who were intended to receive the data,
الذين من المفترض عليهم استقبال البيانات،
74 percent of them received it.
74 في المئة منهم استقبلوها.
96 percent of them
96 في المئة منهم
found it useful.
وجدوها مفيدة.
83 percent of them took action --
83 في المئة منهم تحركوا --
evidence that it is indeed empowering.
كدليل على أنها بالفعل ممكّنة.
And 73 percent of them shared it.
و73 في المئة منهم شاركوها.
The TERA system
نظام تيرا
was developed from Haiti
تم تطويره في هاييتي
with support of engineers in the region.
بدعم من مهندسين في المنطقة.
It is a user-appropriate technology
إنها تكنولوجيا مناسبة للمستخدم
that has been used for humanitarian good to great effect.
والتي تم استمعالها في خير الأعمال الإنسانية بتأثير عظيم.
Technology is transformational.
التكنولوجيا تحويلية.
Right across the developing world,
في جميع أرجاء العالم النامي،
citizens and communities
المواطنون والمجتمعات
are using technology
يستخدمون التكنولوجيا
to enable them to bring about change, positive change,
لتمكينهم من إحداث التغيير، التغيير الإيجابي،
in their own communities.
في مجتمعاتهم الخاصة.
The grassroots has been strengthened
تمت تقوية القاعدة
through the social power of sharing
من خلال القوة الاجتماعية للتشارك
and they are challenging the old models,
وهي تهدد النماذج القديمة،
the old analog models
النماذج التناظرية القديمة
of control and command.
للتحكم والسيطرة.
One illustration of the transformational power of technology
أحد الأمثلة على القوة التحويلية للتكنولوجيا
is in Kibera.
هي في كيبيرا.
Kibera is one of Africa's largest slums.
كيبيرا هي إحدى أكبر الأحياء الفقيرة في أفريقيا.
It's on the outskirts of Nairobi,
إنها توجد على ضواحي نيروبي،
the capital city of Kenya.
عاصمة كينيا.
It's home to an unknown number of people --
إنها مسكن لعدد غير معروف من الناس --
some say between 250,000
بعضهم يقول 250,000
and 1.2 million.
و 1.2 مليون.
If you were to arrive in Nairobi today
إن كنت لتصل إلى نيروبي اليوم
and pick up a tourist map,
وتلتقط خريطة سياحية،
Kibera is represented
كيبيرا ممثلة
as a lush, green national park
على شكل منطقة خضراء، متنزه وطني أخضر
devoid of human settlement.
خال من المستوطنات البشرية.
Young people living in Kibera
الشباب الذين يعيشون في كيبيريا
in their community,
في مجتمعهم،
with simple handheld devices,
بأجهزة محمولة بسيطة،
GPS handheld devices and SMS-enabled mobile phones,
أجهزة تحديد المواقع الجغرافية المحمولة والهواتف بخدمة الرسائل النصية،
have literally put themselves on the map.
وضعوا أنفسهم حرفيا على الخريطة.
They have collated crowd-sourced data
قاموا بجمع بيانات حشودية المصدر
and rendered the invisible visible.
وحولوا الغير مرئي إلى مرئي.
People like Josh and Steve
أشخاص مثل جوش وستيف
are continuing to layer information upon information,
يواصلون تصفيف المعلومات تلو المعلومات،
real-time information, Tweet it and text it onto these maps
معلومات بالوقت الحقيقي، تغريدات تويتر ورسائل نصية في هذه الخرائط
for all to use.
لتستخدم جميعها.
You can find out about the latest impromptu music session.
يمكن أن تعرف بخصوص آخر جلسة للموسيقى المرتجلة.
You can find out about the latest security incident.
يمكن أن تعرف بخصوص آخر حادث أمني.
You can find out about places of worship.
يمكن أن تعرف بخصوص أماكن العبادة.
You can find out about the health centers.
يمكن أن تعرف بخصوص المراكز الصحية.
You can feel the dynamism
يمكن أن تحس بحركية
of this living, breathing community.
هذا المجتمع الحي المتنفس.
They also have their own news network on YouTube
لديهم كذلك شبكة أخبارهم الخاصة على اليوتيوب
with 36,000 viewers at the moment.
ب 36,000 مشاهد لحد الآن.
They're showing us what can be done
إنهم يروننا ما يمكن أن يتم
with mobile, digital technologies.
بالتكنولوجيات الرقمية والمحمولة.
They're showing that the magic of technology
إنهم يروننا أن سحر التكنولوجيا
can bring the invisible visible.
يمكن أن يجعل المخفي مرئيا.
And they are giving a voice to themselves.
وهم يجعلون صوتا لأنفسهم.
They are telling their own story,
إنهم يروون قصتهم،
bypassing the official narrative.
متجاوزين الرواية الرسمية.
And we're seeing from all points on the globe similar stories.
ونحن نرى قصصا مماثلة من كل النقاط على الأرض.
In Mongolia for instance,
في منغوليا على سبيل المثال،
where 30 percent of the people are nomadic,
حيث 30 في المئة من الناس من الرحل،
SMS information systems are being used
أنظمة المعلومات المعتمدة على الرسائل النصية تستخدم
to track migration and weather patterns.
لتعقب أنماط الهجرة والطقس.
SMS is even used
الرسائل النصية تستخدم حتى
to hold herder summits
في احتواء قمم الرعاة
from remote participation.
من أماكن متنقلة.
And if people are migrating
وإن كان الناس يهاجرون
into urban, unfamiliar, concrete environments,
إلى أوساط ملموسة حضرية وغير مألوفة،
they can also be helped in anticipation
يمكنهم كذلك الحصول على المساعدة في الاستباق
with social supporters ready and waiting for them
مع مساندين اجتماعيين مستعدين وفي انتظارهم
based on SMS knowledge.
بالاعتماد على معرفة الرسائل النصية.
In Nigeria,
في نيجيريا،
open-source SMS tools
أدوات الرسائل النصية المفتوحة المصدر
are being used by the Red Cross community workers
يتم استخدامها من قبل عمال مجتمع الصليب الأحمر
to gather information from the local community
لجمع المعلومات من المجتمع المحلي
in an attempt to better understand and mitigate
في محاولة لفهم والتخفيف بشكل أفضل
the prevalence of malaria.
من انتشار الملاريا.
My colleague, Jason Peat, who runs this program,
زميلي، جايسون بيت والذي يدير هذا البرنامج،
tells me it's 10 times faster and 10 times cheaper
أخبرني أنها أرخص وأسرع بعشر مرات
than the traditional way of doing things.
من الطرق التقليدية للقيام بهذه الأمور.
And not only is it empowering to the communities,
وهي ليست فقط ممكنّة للمجتمعات
but really importantly,
لكنها مهمة للغاية،
this information stays in the community
هذه المعلومات تبقى في المجتمع
where it is needed to formulate long-term health polices.
حيث الحاجة إليها لصياغة سياسات صحية على المدى الطويل.
We are on a planet
نحن على كوكب
of seven billion people,
يتألف من سبع مليار شخص،
five billion mobile subscriptions.
خمس مليار مشترك في شبكات الهاتف المحمول.
By 2015,
بحلول 2015،
there will be three billion smartphones in the world.
سيكون هناك ثلاث مليار هاتف ذكي في العالم.
The U.N. broadband commission
لجنة النطاق العريض في الأمم المتحدة
has recently set targets
قد وضعت مؤخرا أهدافا
to help broadband access
لمساعدة الوصول إلى النطاق العريض
in 50 percent of the Developing World,
في 50 في المئة من العالم النامي،
compared to 20 percent today.
بالمقارنة مع 20 في المئة اليوم.
We are hurtling towards a hyper-connected world
نحن نندفع نحو عالم شديد الاتصال
where citizens from all cultures and all social strata
حيث المواطنون من كل الثقافات وكل الطبقات الاجتماعية
will have access to smart, fast mobile devices.
سيستطيعون الوصول إلى أجهزة محمولة ذكية وسريعة.
People are understanding,
الناس يفهمون،
from Cairo to Oakland,
من القاهرة إلى اوكلاند،
that there are new ways to come together,
أن هناك طرقا جديدة للتوحد،
there are new ways to mobilize,
هناك طرق جديدة للتحرك،
there are new ways to influence.
هناك طرق جديدة للتأثير.
A transformation is coming which needs to be understood
هناك تحول قادم يحتاج إلى استيعاب
by the humanitarian structures and humanitarian models.
من طرف البنية الإنسانية والنماذج الإنسانية.
The collective voices of people
الأصوات الجماعية للناس
needs to be more integrated through new technologies
تحتاج أن تكون أكثر تكاملا عن طريق تكنولوجيات جديدة
into the organizational strategies and plans of actions
في الاستراتيجيات التنظيمية وخطط تنفيذ العمل
and not just recycled
وليس فقط إعادة تدويرها
for fundraising or marketing.
من أجل جمع التبرعات أو التسويق.
We need to, for example, embrace
نحتاج، على سبيل المثال، إلى احتضان
the big data,
البيانات الضخمة،
the knowledge that is there from market leaders
المعرفة المتوفرة من قادة السوق
who understand what it means
الذين يفهمون مالذي يعنيه
to use and leverage big data.
استخدام واستغلال البيانات الضخمة.
One idea that I'd like you to consider, for instance,
فكرة واحدة أريد منكم اعتبارها، على سبيل المثال،
is to take a look at our IT departments.
هو إلقاء نظرة على إدارات تكنولوجيا المعلومات الخاصة بنا.
They're normally backroom or basement hardware service providers,
هي عادة غرف خلفية أو قبو مزودي خدمات العتاد الصلب،
but they need to be elevated to software strategists.
لكنها تحتاج إلى أن ترتقي إلى استراتيجيات البرمجيات.
We need people in our organizations
نحتاج في هيئاتنا إلى أشخاص
who know what it's like to work with big data.
يعرفون ما يعنيه العمل مع بيانات ضخمة.
We need technology
نحتاج التكنولوجيا
as a core organizational principle.
كمبدأ تنظيمي جوهري.
We need technological strategists in the boardroom
نحتاج الاستراتيجيات التكنولوجيا في مجلس الإدارة
who can ask and answer the question,
يمكن أن نسأل ونجيب عن سؤال،
"What would Amazon or Google
"ما الذي قد يفعله غوغل أو أمازون
do with all of this data?"
بكل هذه البيانات؟"
and convert it to humanitarian good.
وتحويلها إلى خير الإنسانية.
The possibilities
الإمكانيات
that new digital technologies are bringing
التي تتيحها التكنولوجيات الرقمية
can help humanitarian organizations,
يمكنها مساعدة الهيئات الإنسانية،
not only ensure
ليس فقط ضمان
that people's right to information is met,
أن حق الناس في المعلومة قد تحقق،
or that they have their right to communicate,
أو أن لهم الحق في التواصل،
but I think in the future,
لكنني أعتقد أنهم في المستقبل
humanitarian organizations will also have to anticipate
الهيئات الإنسانية ستتوقع كذلك
the right for people to access
حق الناس في الوصول
critical communication technologies
إلى تكنولوجيا التواصل الحساسة
in order to ensure
من أجل ضمان
that their voices are heard,
إسماع أصواتهم،
that they're truly participating,
أنهم يشاركون حقا
that they're truly empowered in the humanitarian world.
أنهم ممكّنون في العالم الإنساني.
It has always been the elusive ideal
دائما ما كان مثاليا وبعيد المنال
to ensure full participation of people affected by disasters
ضمان المشاركة الكاملة للأشخاص المتضررين من الكوارث
in the humanitarian effort.
في الجهود الإنسانية.
We now have the tools. We now have the possibilities.
لدينا الآن الأدوات. لدينا الآن الإمكانيات.
There are no more reasons not to do it.
ليست هناك أسباب أخرى لعدم القيام بذلك.
I believe we need to bring the humanitarian world
أعتقد أننا نحتاج أن نأتي بعالم الأعمال الإنسانية
from analog to digital.
من التناظري إلى الرقمي.
Thank you very much.
شكرا جزيلا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)